Jacob Lawrence Papers
Jacob Lawrence Papers
1937-1995
Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-2000.
4.5 linear ft.
Spanning 1937-1971, the Jacob Lawrence Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, artwork reproductions, writings, printed material, and memorabilia of the African-American painter, printmaker, and artist.
143292
Biographical History
Jacob Lawrence (1917-2000) was a leading black American artist, working in gouache, an opaque water colour, and tempera, a mixture of pigment and a binder. He was famous for the distinctive flat surfaces of his narrative paintings depicting social problems, as in The Migration of the Negro (1940-1941) and Struggle: From the History of the American People (1955). Lawrence was born in Atlantic City, New Jersey. He studied under Charles Alston at the Art Workshop in Harlem, New York (1932-1939), and at the Harlem Art Center and the American Artists School in New York City (1937-1939). He was a professor of art emeritus at the University of Washington, Seattle. [From Hutchinson Encyclopedia of Biography (2000)]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jacob Lawrence Papers consist of Biographical data, Correspondence, Artwork (reproductions), Memorabilia, Printed material and Writings of the African-American painter, printmaker, and artist. Born in Atlantic City, New Jersey, in 1917, Jacob Lawrence was an alumnus of the Harlem Workshop and the WPA Federal Art Project. The collection reflects not only the development of his artistic career, but also the social climate of the American art scene from the Depression through the early 1970s.
Two folders of Biographical data begin the collection.
Spanning 1937 through 1971, the Correspondence is almost exclusively of a business nature and comprises incoming letters and a few drafts of Lawrence's outgoing responses. Arranged chronologically (a selected name index appears at the end of this inventory), correspondents includes art historians (Alfred H. Barr, David C. Driskell, Creighton Gilbert, Abram Lerner, Alain Locke, Lee Nordness, Regenia A. Perry) and artists (Charles Alston, Benny Andrews, Romare Bearden, Lizzie Borden, Frank Bowling, Gerard Charriere, Claude Clark, Hy Cohen, Ernest Crichlow, Miki Denhof, Fritz Eichenberg, Philip Evergood, Elton C. Fax, Chuck Forsman, Harry Gottlieb, Eugene Grigsby, Joseph Hirsch, Carl Holty, Joe Lasker, Jack Levine, Frank Mechau, Earl Miller, Gregorio Prestopino, Charles Sheeler, Vincent Smith, Moses Soyer, Raphael Soyer, May Stevens, Walter Williams, Ed Wilson, Richard Yarde); as well as authors and poets (Miriam Biskin, Mildred Cummings, Harold Ehrensperger, M. A. Harris, Harry B. Henderson, Langston Hughes, Raymond Patterson, Margaret Rigg). Lawrence also received correspondence from educational institutions at which he has held teaching positions (Art Students League, Brandeis University, Denison University, Five Towns Music and Art Foundation, Inc., New School for Social Research, Pratt Institute, Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture); foundations and institutions which have awarded him grants and/or fellowships (American Artists School, American Academy of Arts and Letters, Chapelbrook Foundation, Ford Foundation, John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, Julius Rosenwald Fund, National Institute of Arts and Letters); galleries which represented his work (Downtown Gallery, Alan Gallery, Terry Dintenfass, Inc.); museums which have purchased and/or exhibited his work (Art Institute of Chicago, Brooklyn Museum, Carnegie Institute, Detroit Institute of Arts, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of Fine Arts (Boston), Museum of Modern Art, North Carolina Museum of Art, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Whitney Museum of American Art); and institutions and publications which support and promote the study of Afro-American art and culture (American Society of African Culture, Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Freedomways, Museum of African Art, Opportunity, National Urban League). In addition, Lawrence was approached by many local, national, and international organizations, from New York City high schools and churches to the Institute of International Education, to serve as a juror for art shows and the awarding of scholarships.
Artwork consists of reproductions of Lawrence's work, and features photographs, printed items, and slides. The photographs include images of both Lawrence's painting and a number of interior shots of gallery and museum shows. Printed material of Lawrence's work includes post cards, greeting cards, magazine covers, and appearances in various art and general publications which have illustrative material with minimal text.
Memorabilia comprises awards, financial material, non-exhibition-related invitations, personal photographs, printed material, and manuscript writings about Lawrence by others. Printed material contains magazine articles about Lawrence (1939-1969) from various general and art periodicals, newspaper clippings (1937-1970), and programs and calendars from public events at which Lawrence spoke or was honored.
In their original state, the Lawrence Papers contained three scrapbooks which held a variety of materials, including correspondence, exhibition announcements and catalogs, magazine appearances, and newspaper clippings, which documented the early stages of his career (pre-1950). In the interest of preservation, the scrapbooks were dismantled and the materials integrated into various parts of the collection.
Printed material, consisting of academic brochures and course catalogs, exhibition announcements, invitations, catalogs, and posters, reflects Lawrence's dual career as teacher and artist. Course catalogs include those of Brandeis University (1965), the New School (1966-1969), and Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture (1968-1970). Exhibition announcements, invitations, and catalogs, document the course of Lawrence's artistic career, and include catalogs from his first one-man exhibition in 1938 sponsored by the James Wheldon Johnson Literary Guild at the Harlem YMCA, the American Negro Exposition (1939) in Chicago, at which he won second prize, and many other exhibition catalogs of one-man and group shows from the late 1930s through 1971. The collection also contains posters for two of his shows.
Writings include interviews, speeches, and miscellaneous manuscripts which suggest Lawrence's philosophy about his work.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Other series are arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Separated Material
A number of printed items, including a copy of Federico García Lorca's Gypsy ballads translated by Langston Hughes and signed/inscribed by him to Lawrence, have been removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to and search on "Gift of Jacob Lawrence" to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; African Americans; Literature -- Children's; Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-2000.; Locke, Alain, 1885-1954.; Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988.; Eichenberg, Fritz, 1901-1990.; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973.; Fax, Elton C.; Sheeler, Charles, 1883-1965.; Soyer, Moses, 1899-1974.; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Patterson, Raymond R.; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.); New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture.; Julius Rosenwald Fund; Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.); American Society of African Culture.; Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, inc.; Freedomways Associates.; Museum of African Art (U.S.); National Urban League.; African American art.; African American artists.; African American painting.; African American printmakers.; African Americans -- Biography.; Art, American.; Art and race.; Art -- American Exhibitions.; Art -- American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States -- 20th century.; Painting -- Study and teaching.; Painting, American -- Afro-American painting.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Printmakers -- United States.; Announcements.; Articles.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); College catalogs.; Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Interviews.; Invitations.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Speeches (documents); Artists.; Painters.; Printmakers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jacob Lawrence, 1963, 1966, 1971.
Ramie Streng letter (2/20/1995) gift of Ramie Streng, 2014.
Inventory
- Biographical data
  - Compiled by the American Federation of the Arts (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1937; 1940-1949,; 1952-1956,; 1958-1966,; undated; 19 folders (Box 1)
  - General, 1967-1971; 1995; 14 folders (Box 2)
    Ramie Streng letter (2/20/1995) gift of Ramie Streng, 2014.
  - General, undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
- Artwork (reproductions)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Printed material, oversize (Oversize 1)
  - Slides, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards (Box 3)
  - Awards, Committee for the Negro in the Arts (Oversize 1)
  - Financial (Box 3)
  - Invitations, non-exhibition related, 1946; 1962-1969 (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Photographs, photo of Lawrence with students in a classroom (Oversize 1)
  - Printed material
    - Articles about, 1939-1957; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Articles about, 1958-1969; undated; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Books about
      - Jacob Lawrence by Aline Saarinen, page proofs (Box 4)
      - Peripheral mention, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1937-1960; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1961-1970; undated; 11 folders (Box 5)
    - Programs, calendars, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous about JL (Box 5)
  - Writings by others
    - Gypsy ballads by Federico García Lorca, translated by Langston Hughes (Beloit Poetry Journal Chapbook No. 1), inscribed presentation copy from Hughes to Lawrence
      Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging; please refer to to locate this item.
    - Typescripts, various (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 items (Box 5)
- Printed material
  - Academic brochures, course catalogs
    - Brandeis University, 1965 (Box 5)
    - New School, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
    - Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, 1968-1970; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Exhibition announcements, invitations, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1937-1960; 19 folders (Box 6)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1961-1969; undated; 11 folders (Box 7)
  - Exhibition posters (Box 7)
- Writings
  - Interview, 1967; undated (Box 7)
  - Speeches (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
Selected Index to Correspondence
Abernathy, Ralph David 11 June 1968 1 Oct. 1968
Alan Gallery 20 June 1955 23 Sept. 1955
Alston, Charles 12 Oct. 1970
American Artists School 26 Aug. 1937
American Negro Exposition 6 Aug. 1940 23 Aug. 1940
Ames, Elizabeth 10 Jan. 1953 7 Jan. 1954
Andrews, Benny 12 Dec. 1966
Art in America 15 July 1963
Barr, Alfred Hamilton 24 Nov. 1945
Bearden, Romare H. 19 May 1965 9 Apr. 1971 undated (3)
Biskin, Miriam 2 Feb. 1964
Bocour, Leonard 21 May 1965
Borden, Lizzie undated
Bowling, Frank 15 Dec. 1966
Burns, Andrew 5 Feb. 1953 31 Jan. 1956 3 Feb. 1965
Carty, Leo S. 4 Mar. 1970
Chamberlain, Betty 23 Feb. 1971
Charriere, Gerard 12 Feb. 1970
Chase, Judith Wragg 19 Feb. 1971
Clark, Claude 26 June 1968 7 Aug. 1968 30 Nov. 1968 2 Feb. 1969 7 Feb. 1969 17 May 1969
Cohen, Hy 11 Mar. 1966 22 Mar. 1966 9 June 1967 29 Mar. 1968
Crichlow, Ernest T. 2 Nov. 1961
Cummings, Mildred H. 16 Mar. 1968 11 Apr. 1968 4 July 1968 13 July 1968
Davis, Robert Tyler 8 Nov. 1945
Denhof, Miki undated
Downtown Gallery See Halpert, Edith Gregor
Davis, Stuart 1945 Sept. 30
Driskell, David C. 7 May 1962 7 May 1968 31 May 1968 26 June 1968 11 Sept. 1968 18 Oct. 1968 21 Nov. 1968 19 Dec. 1968 10 May 1969 14 July 1969
Ehrensperger, Harold 18 Nov. 1949
Eichenberg, Fritz 24 Mar. 1964 1 Sept. 1964 21 Apr. 1969
Evergood, Philip 21 Oct. 1963 17 Nov. 1963 23 Nov. 1964 5 Feb. 1965 8 Mar. 1965
Fax, Elton C. 7 Apr. 1967 9 Aug. 1967 15 Aug. 1967
Forsman, Chuck undated
Fortune 1 July 1941 6 June 1947
Gahagan, James E. 13 Apr. 1969
Gaither, Edmund B. 29 Oct. 1969
Gilbert, Creighton 25 Sept. 1964 19 Oct. 1964 28 Dec. 1964 8 Jan. 1965 26 Jan. 1965 26 Aug. 1968
Gonzalez, Xavier 16 Dec. 1966 26 Dec. 1966
Gottlieb, Harry 4 Oct. 1937
Grigsby, Eugene Howard 22 Aug. 1968 11 Nov. 1968
Gwathmey, Rosalie (Mrs. Robert) undated (2)
Halpert, Edith Gregor 15 Dec. 1941 12 Feb. 1942 12 Mar. 1942 4 June 1948 1 Apr. 1961 13 July 1964 31 Aug. 1964 undated
Harris, M. A. 20 Nov. 1967
Henderson, Harry Brinton 17 Nov. 1970 4 Jan. 1971
Hirsch, Joseph undated
Hirshhorn, Joseph H. 8 Apr. 1968
Holty, Carl 22 May 1969
Hough, Winston Harry undated
Hughes, Langston 26 Feb. 1966
Jefferson, Louise E. 11 Feb. 1969
Kent, Norman 17 Apr. 1970
Koch, John 24 Nov. 1969
Julius Rosenwald Fund 17 Apr. 1940 11 Apr. 1941 18 Apr. 1942
Lasker, Joe 11 Dec. 1968
Lerner, Abram 3 Feb. 1960
Levine, Jack 9 May 1966 undated
Lindsay, John V. 26 Sept. 1968
Lion, Stephan 20 Sept. 1968
Lipman, Jean See Art in America.
Locke, Alain LeRoy 11 Nov. 1948 undated
Mayor, A. Hyatt 23 July 1962 2 Aug. 1962 10 Sept. 1962
Mebane, Mary E. 30 Mar. 1964
Mechau, Frank 24 Apr. 1940 23 Sept. 1940
Meltzer, Milton 29 Apr. 1966
Miller, Earl 14 Jan. 1968
Moore, Trevor Wyatt 14 Mar. 1965
Nordness, Lee 15 Jan. 1962 18 July 1962
O'Connor, Francis V. Mar./Apr. 1968
Patterson, Raymond 9 Jan. 1968 4 May 1968 18 Oct. 1968 6 Mar. 1969 14 June 1969
Penney, Edmund F. 2 Apr. 1970
Perry, Regenia Alfreda 8 Mar. 1971
Pratt Institute 7 June 1956 2 Oct. 1958 Aug. 1962 Aug. 1963 21 Nov. 1963 18 Feb. 1965 8 July 1965 29 June 1966 24 May 1968 10 June 1969 17 June 1971 15 Sept. 1970
Prestopino, Gregorio undated
Randolph, A. Philip 14 Oct. 1970
Rigg, Margaret 18 Jan. 1962 20 Mar. 1962 25 Sept. 1962 18 Oct. 1962 12 July 1963 8 Oct. 1963 24 Sept. 1970
Ross, John 1 June 1964 30 Apr. 1968
Sheeler, Charles undated
Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture 13 Apr. 1967 26 Sept. 1968 4 Aug. 1967 7 Nov. 1967 16 Nov. 1967 24 Nov. 1967 5 Nov. 1968 1 Apr. 1969 16 Feb. 1971 undated
Smith, Joseph A. undated
Smith, Vincent 28 Dec. 1967 29 Mar. 1968
Soyer, Moses undated
Soyer, Raphael 21 Nov. 1968
Spingarn, Amy undated
Stevens, May 26 Aug. 1968
Taylor, Francis Henry 5 Nov. 1945
Terry Dintenfass, Inc. 5 Feb. 1963 23 Apr. 1963 9 May 1963 13 July 1964 30 Sept. 1964 6 Mar. 1965 9 Mar. 1965 11 Mar. 1965 4 May 1965
United States Committee for the First World Festival of Negro Arts, Inc. 12 Oct. 1964 beg. 1966 11 Mar. 1966 17 Aug. 1966
Walker, Constance 1 Oct. 1968
Williams, Walter 27 May 1969
Wilson, Ed 23 Dec. 1967 11 Mar. 1969
Yarde, Richard 19 Oct. 1967